Velian Pandeliev

www.velian.ca • vpandeliev@gmail.com • (647) 864 1472

SUMMARY

A versatile professional trained in user experience design with a background in computer science and cognitive psychology, and with three years of experience teaching the fundamentals of human-computer interaction, who has demonstrated an ability to gather rich user insights; convert them into solutions through research, prototyping, and evaluation; and present them to team members, stakeholders, clients, and executives.

SKILLS AND ABILITIES

User Research

- Conducting primary user research through interviews, surveys, and user observation
- Conducting secondary user research and performing competitor analysis
- Distilling insights into personas, experience maps, user journeys, job stories, or themes
- Evaluating interfaces through A/B testing, heuristic evaluation, usability testing

User Experience Design

- Iterating on design through ideation, wireframes, storyboards, and mockups
- Rapid prototyping using paper, HTML/CSS/JS, InVision, Balsamiq, Bootstrap
- User interface design in Sketch, Illustrator and Photoshop

Technical Skills

- Web development with HTML/CSS/JavaScript, jQuery, React, Django
- Programming experience in Python, Java, JavaScript
- Proficiency in version control, unit testing, productivity software, *nix shell
- Studied and taught object-oriented programming, algorithmic complexity, data structures, and memory management

Interpersonal Skills

- Proven ability to engage with users to identify user pain points, needs, and workflows
- Excellent communication skills demonstrated while interfacing with clients, stakeholders, team members, and executives
- Experience developing and delivering impactful presentations to any targeted audience
- Track record in interdisciplinary collaboration, including in agile/scrum environments
- In-depth experience mentoring and teaching on a wide range of topics and for various skill levels

WORK EXPERIENCE

Lecturer, Human-Computer Interaction

Department of Computer Science, University of Toronto (2014-2017)

- Taught the fundamentals of UX research, design, and evaluation including User-Centered Design, research methods, ideation, prototyping, usability testing, and interface design
- Lectured over 1000 third-year computer science students over 5 semesters
- Provided one-on-one mentoring and support to students in independent projects

User Experience Research Intern

Immersive Experiences Lab, HP Inc. (Summer 2016)

- Performed in-depth qualitative research on 31 Bay Area creative professionals
- Generated rich insights into designer tools and workflows
- Presented results to stakeholders and executives to guide the creation of new products

User Experience Intern

Cloud Platform Business Unit, VMware, Inc. (Summer 2015)

- Performed primary user research and analysis, and synthesized the findings
- Developed an experience map of the trust relationship between users and decisionsupporting dashboards in order to illustrate system administrator reluctance to adopt new solutions
- Analyzed and presented attendance data and feedback from an internal UX conference

Bilingual Alignment and HTML Standards Intern

Communication and Library Services, Statistics Canada (May 2008 – April 2009)

- Collaborated with natural language processing researchers and data scientists to automate page alignment between English and French documents
- Assisted in verifying HTML standards compliance in daily government publications

Simulation Support Technician

Advanced Cognitive Engineering Lab, Carleton University (Summer 2007 - Summer 2008)

- Conducted cognitive psychology research on operator attention and distraction with drivers and helicopter pilots
- Built and prototyped simulations and experimental scenarios

Research Assistant

Centre for Applied Cognitive Research, Carleton University (Summer 2006)

- Programmed lab experiments on mathematical cognition and numeracy
- Conducted lab experiments and debriefing sessions

EDUCATION

Doctoral Research, Computer Science (Human-Computer Interaction) University of Toronto, Toronto, ON

Withdrawn in good standing (ABD)

- Spearheaded research on interfaces to support the companion activities of responsive reading, i.e., non-linear navigation, superimposed annotation, spatial arrangement
- Completed courses on research methods, serious games, reading comprehension and cognition, and novel interaction techniques
- Supervised a dozen undergraduate projects in areas such as responsive reading, educational technology and law
- Presented, volunteered, and reviewed submissions for multiple HCI conferences
- Reviewed candidates for the department's M.Sc. in Applied Computing program

M.Sc. Computer Science (Human-Computer Interaction) University of Toronto, Toronto, ON

Supervisor: Prof. Ronald Baecker

- Developed an online portal to evaluate the effectiveness of mental fitness games on cognitive function in the elderly
- Validated the prototype with six senior users
- Presented results at multiple conferences on serious games, cognitive health, and humancomputer interaction

B.A. Cognitive Science (Cognition & Computation) Carleton University, Ottawa, ON

Graduated with High Distinction

- Earned an interdisciplinary degree encompassing computer science, artificial intelligence, neuroscience, cognitive psychology, and philosophy of mind
- Successfully completed an Honours project on the effects of visual or auditory distraction on drivers in a state-of-the-art driving simulator
- Awarded the Senate Medal for Outstanding Academic Achievement

REFERENCES

Alexander Thayer, Immersive Experiences Lab, HP Inc. (alexander.thayer@hp.com)

Paul Gries, Department of Computer Science, University of Toronto (pgries@cs.toronto.edu)

Ricardo Jota, Dynamic Graphics Project, University of Toronto (jotacosta@dgp.toronto.edu)